Curriculum Vitae

Fabian van den Berg



Oranjeplein 266 6224KZ Maastricht Netherlands



+31638247657



fabian.c.g.vandenberg@gmail.com









Summary

As a motivated, creative, and flexible PhD researcher, I have a strong affinity for experimental design and a deep understanding of quantitative methodological and analytical processes. During my work, I examine existing data and literature to identify research gaps, generate hypotheses, and define tasks and goals to answer questions with collected data.

My work required me to learn new quantitative methods, learn new programming languages, and develop pipelines to be as efficient as possible, all skill that I would gladly put to good use. In addition, I have developed leadership and teaching skills, working in teams with varied strengths, and fostered strong social bonds.

- Skills in experimental design, data collection, and statistical analysis
- A good grip on programming languages for data manipulation and computation statistics (Matlab, Python, R)
- Strong interpersonal skills that help me to forge strong bonds within a team and engage with an audience when presenting new information.

Highlights

- Experience in *various research studies* involving the design, execution, and analysis of Autonomic, Behavioral, and Cognitive measures.
- **Analyses of datasets** using advanced statistical methods, both parametric and non-parametric, and the reporting of the results concisely and understandably.
- **Presenting results** at symposia and conferences to a non-expert audience using non-scientific language, yet still explaining the relevance and meaning of the results.
- Teaching experience in problem-based learning on various topics within psychology, neuroscience, and statistics, and being nominated for the 2020 teaching award. In addition, I Developed a PhD-level course on advanced statistical methods, supervised and trained students in the adequate use of EEG data acquisition, and trained interns to perform neuropsychological assessments from testing to diagnosis.

Work Experience

PhD Candidate

Maastricht University

During a PhD, existing data and literature are examined to identify research gaps in order to generate hypotheses. Based on this research, specific tasks and goals are defined, and data is collected.

17-10-2016 to present

For this project, behavioral and neural (EEG) data were collected, processed, and analyzed using advanced quantitative methods. The results were interpreted and communicated back to experts through scientific papers and non-experts through presentations.

In addition, a portion of the work involved teaching, which focused on Psychology, Statistics, research methods, and computer skills (such as excel).

 Created and taught a new course in Linear Mixed Models for repeated measures designs

Statistician

Hulp bij SPSS / Solid Statistics

- Statistical analyses for various types of datasets
- · Complex statistical analyses for medical data
- Maintenance and writing for the website

01-05-2015 to 17-10-2016

Freelance Work

Digitizing of screening questionnaires

01-8-2014 to 01-05-2015

01-10-2013 to 31-7-2014

• Statistical analyses and consultation of various kinds of datasets

Combined Clinical and Research Internship

KNP Practice for Child Neuro Psychology

- Setting up neuropsychological assessments
- Administering neuropsychological tests
- · Interpreting and reporting the results
- Data collection, analysis, and interpretation for scientific research.

Tutor Faculty of Psychology

01-09-2011 to 01-10-2013

06-02-2011 to 01-10-2013

Maastricht University

Guiding problem-based tutorial groups

Student Assistant Psychology

Maastricht University

- Creating Questionnaires
- Digitizing Questionnaires for research
- Creating a data conversion and processing program

MARBLE project followed by Research Assistant

Maastricht University

- Testing participants (heartrate, skin-conductance, and respiration)
- · Administering questionnaires
- Analyzing data (BrainVision Analyzer 2.0, Matlab, SPSS)
- Presenting preliminary results on the international student research conference 2012 (poster presentation)

2

Research Elective (effects of sleep deprivation on driving)

01-10-2012 to 01-06-2013

Maastricht University

 Acquiring data in a moving car (EEG) and a lab environment (reaction times, various tasks, questionnaires)

Education

Research Masters Cognitive and Clinical Neuroscience: Neuropsychology track

01-09-2012 to 31-8-2014

Maastricht University

Completed 31 July 2014 - Diploma received 19 September 2014

Master thesis: The predictive value of fluid intelligence, attention, and

memory on academic performance

Minor thesis: Using existing screening tools to differentiate between

learning disorders and non-verbal learning disability

Bachelor in Psychology

01-09-2009 to 01-07-2012

Maastricht University

Completed 1st July 2012 – Diploma received 20 October 2012

Bachelor thesis: Improving the Concealed Information Test

Skills

Technical skills Applications

Office, SPSS, R, Matlab, BrainVision Analyzer, Photoshop

Programming

Analytic: R, Python, Matlab, SPSS-syntax

Advanced: VB.net (VBA; Excel), Java (incl. Google App Script)

Intermediate: HTML, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery

Research Skills Research Projects

Involved in and supervised several projects covering

Behavioral, Cognitive, and neuropsychological testing

Data collected using surveys, Autonomic Measures (EEG,

Heartrate, Skin-Conductance), and Behavioral Tasks

Advanced knowledge of statistical methods, including but not limited to Regression (Mixed, multilevel, Logistic, Ordinal, Multinomial), Analysis of Variance, and non-parametric testing

Presentation of Results

Experience presenting results on symposia and conferences,

internationally and locally

Teaching Skills Problem Based Learning

Guiding problems-based tutorial groups in a variety of subjects (12-14 students per group) in areas of Biological Psychology, Social Psychology, Developmental Psychology, and Statistics

Courses and Practicals

Conceived and developed a PhD-level course in Linear Mixed Regression Models, consisting of four lectures and study

materials

Involved in the automation of the bachelor level Excel-practical, adding self-check tools and guides for students to receive

immediate feedback on their performance.

Supervision

Co-supervised two groups of students, teaching them the correct use of EEG equipment and how to acquire clean data.

Co-supervised master students, designing and coding behavioral tasks and teaching them how to acquire data from young children (4-6 years of age)

Neuropsychological Assessment Training

Personally trained interns to perform neuropsychological assessments, the use of various measurement tools, and determining a clinical diagnosis based on the results

Other Skills

Languages

Native Language: Dutch Advanced/fluent: English

Passive: German

Clinical Experience

Awarded the Dutch psychodiagnostic certificate (Basis Aantekening Psychodiagnostiek; BAPD)
Creating and administering neuropsychological assessments.
Data analysis, interpretation, and translation into a report

Publications

- Van Mier, H. I., Schleepen, T. M., & Van den Berg, F. C. (2019). Gender differences regarding the impact of math anxiety on arithmetic performance in second and fourth graders. *Frontiers in psychology*, 9, 2690.
- van den Berg, F. C., de Weerd, P., & Jonkman, L. M. (2020). Number-related Brain Potentials Are Differentially Affected by Mapping Novel Symbols on Small versus Large Quantities in a Number Learning Task. *Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience*, 1-13.
- van den Berg, F. C. G., De Weerd, P., & Jonkman, L. M. (2020, August 6). Behavioral and event-related-brain potential evidence for facilitating effects of canonical finger-number configurations on young adult's number processing in a Math verification task. https://doi.org/10.31219/osf.io/xmg7e